Ruben Esteche

🕈 Sao Paulo, Brazil 🗷 rubenesteche@hotmail.com 🔲 +55 (085) 9 91125595 🛅 in/rubenesteche/ 🕳 https://github.com/REsteche

SUMMARY

I am a passionate machine learning engineer specializing in natural language processing and LLM's with transformers architecture. With a strong background in data science, including 4 years of professional experience and 1 year as a backend developer, I bring a comprehensive skill set to the table.

Collaboration is at the heart of my approach, and I am always willing to work alongside fellow researchers and professionals to drive innovation in our industry. I actively seek opportunities to expand my professional network and stay abreast of the latest advancements. Let's create something remarkable together!

EXPERIENCE

Data Scientist & ML Engineer

NTT Data

January 2023 - Present, São Paulo, Brazil

- Developed chatbot system using a combination of NLP and machine learning (ML), resulting in an accuracy of 92% for classification tasks and 40% reduction in human labor hours.
- Implemented DevOps pipelines for deploying ML models and optimized them by 15%, resulting in improved productivity.
- · Became responsible for overseeing all our Data & MLOps practices during the deployment stages of our product.
- · Developed generative AIaaS solutions in MS format and also ensure seamless support for the project's well-established services.

ML Researcher & Backend Developer

Dell Lead

June 2022 - January 2023, Ceará, Brazil

- · Work on a global scale DELL project named WAL (Website Accessibility Layer).
- · Applied several data science techniques, such as web scraping and machine learning, to enhance the project's capabilities.
- · I applied natural language processing techniques to develop advanced AI models to provide new accessibility tools to our product.
- · I played a crucial role in implementing the NLP models within the project's RESTful API using a microservices architecture.
- · Improved training & inference time of models by 10%, increased compute-efficiency of models by 5%, and improved model accuracy by 8%.

Data Scientist

SUGESTÃO CONSULTORIA

January 2020 - December 2021, Ceará, Brazil

- I took a leadership role in designing and implementing advanced business intelligence strategies, collaborating closely with stakeholders to understand their unique challenges and develop tailored solutions.
- Constructed and modulated accurate predictive models for a wide range of client-defined objectives that achieved a 95% accuracy rate, resulting in an 8% increase in returns.
- Executed comprehensive analysis of existing datasets and produced actionable visualizations to aid in product development and optimization.

Junior Data Scientist

SUGESTÃO CONSULTORIA

January 2019 - December 2019, Ceará, Brazil

- Responsible for implementing innovative business intelligence solutions for our clients. Using cutting-edge ML algorithms and statistical modeling techniques, I develop predictive models that allow our clients to make data-driven decisions and optimize their operations.
- Developed predictive models with up to 95% accuracy, which enabled our clients to forecast customer behavioral patterns and product demand with a 30% increase in precision.
- Reduced the cost of data collection by 25%, enabled automated data pipeline from multiple sources, providing real-time processing and deriving actionable insights necessary for informed decision-making.
- · Improved the speed of data processing by 50%, allowing an increase in customer engagement and retention.

EDUCATION

Master in Theoretical Quantum Physics

Minor in Computational Physics · University of Pernambuco · Recife, PE · 2023

Post Graduation Data Science

Descomplica University · Recife, PE · 2022

Bachelor in Physics

Minor in Physics • Federal University of Pernambuco • Recife, PE • 2020

CERTIFICATIONS

Generative AI Fundamentals

Google Cloud Skills Boost · 2023

The course covers the theoretical concepts behind GANs, LLMs and Stable Diffusion Algorithms, including how they work and their applications in various industries such as art, music, and image generation

School of Research Data Science

ICTP - SAIFR · 2022

The course covers a wide range of topics related to data science, including data acquisition, cleaning, analysis, visualization, and interpretation. Participants also learn essential programming languages and tools used in data science, such as Python, R, and SQL, as well as libraries like Pandas, NumPy, and Matplotlib.

IBM Databases and SQL for Data Science certificate

IBM · 2022

The course shows how to work with various database management systems, such as IBM Db2, SQLite, and PostgreSQL, gaining hands on experience in data manipulation, retrieval, and analysis. The course covers SQL fundamentals, including querying and filtering data, joining tables, and aggregating data to extract meaningful insights.

Convolutional Neural Network with Tensorflow design

Federal University of Ceará · 2020

The CNNs course enables the professional to work with complex data, extracting meaningful features, and building accurate models.

SKILLS

DataScience: NLP, LLMs, CNN, Deep Learning, Machine Learning, Advanced Statistycal Methods, Aglorithms, Modelling Experience, Analytical Tools, Generative AI.

BackEnd: FastAPI, Flask, Django, Redis, MySQL, MongoDB, Cassandra, Postman, Insomnia.

DataOps/MLOps: Docker, Kubernetes, Jenkins.

Cloud: GCP, AWS, AZURE.

Languages: Python, C, C++.

Good comunication skills, able to talk in English, Portuguese, French and Spanish.